Ann Messenger fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
Ann Messenger fonds
1917 - 1999
F-176
Q103826965
1.98 m of textual records 53 photographs 7 negatives
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department Maggie Benston Student Services Building, Rm. 0400 8888 University Dr. Burnaby British Columbia Canada V5A 1S6 Telephone: 778.782.3805 Email: archives@sfu.ca http://www.sfu.ca/archives
PHYSICAL DESCRIPTION Photographs are located in series 1 (sub-series 1 and 2), 6, 7, and 8.
Financial assistance for the arrangement and description of the records and production of the finding aid was generously provided by the Estate of Bill and Ann Messenger.
Messenger, Ann
Ann Carey Messenger was a Professor in the Department of English at Simon Fraser University. She was born in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania on May 31, 1933 to Raymond and Lillian Parshall. Between 1951 and 1955, Messenger attended Oberlin College in Ohio. Awarded a Snell Scholarship for 1952 to 1955, she completed a B.A. in English Literature in 1955. In September of 1955, Messenger began studies at Oxford University in England; she attended Oxford under a Fulbright Scholarship in 1955/56 and a Snell Scholarship in 1956/57. After completing a second B.A. at Oxford, Messenger returned to the United States in 1957, where she procured a job as a secretary at the Princeton University Library Rare Books Department. The following year, in 1958, she began studies at Cornell University. She remained at Cornell for two years, teaching freshman composition and earning credits for an Hon. M.A. at Oxford, which she completed in 1961.
During her first year at Cornell she met William (Bill) Messenger, a fellow graduate English student, and the two were married in Pittsburgh in 1960. After their marriage, they stayed in Pennsylvania, teaching at Bucknell University in Lewisburg for a year, before moving to California. In California, Ann taught, and Bill took post-graduate courses and taught, at the University of California, Berkeley. In September 1963, she began teaching at San Francisco State College. While teaching, she continued working towards her Ph.D., which she was awarded through Cornell University in 1964; Bill completed his PhD. from Berkeley in 1968.
In August 1966 the Messengers moved to Vancouver, British Columbia, to teach at the University of British Columbia (UBC). They immediately fell in love with the city and purchased a home in Point Grey. In September 1968, Messenger secured a job as an Assistant Professor in the English Department at the recently established Simon Fraser University, attaining the rank of Professor in 1973. Her area of expertise as a professor was Restoration and 18th Century literature. In the early 1970s she began to cultivate an interest in the forgotten female writers of the period, and her research developed in this direction. Bill became an Assistant Professor at UBC in 1969, and an Associate Professor in 1982.
In 1988, Messenger was diagnosed with the first of multiple cancers. As a result of her illness, she was unable to teach, and in 1990 she went on long-term disability.
In spite of her illness, her passion for bringing to light female writers of the Restoration and 18th Century encouraged Messenger to continue to write and edit books, papers, and journal articles on the subject, often hiring people to do some of the research that she was unable to carry out herself. These works included the books "His and Hers: Essays in Restoration and Eighteenth Century Literature" (author, published 1986); "Gender at Work: Four Women Writers of the Eighteenth Century" (contributor and editor, published 1990); a new edition of Ellis Cornelia Knight's "Dinarbas"(editor, published 1993); "Woman and Poet in the Eighteenth Century: The Life of Mary Whateley Darwall (1738-1825)" (author, published 1999); "Pastoral Tradition and the Female Talent: Studies in Augustan Poetry" (author, published 1999); and "The Works of Mary Leapor" (co-editor, published 2004).
In 1993, Messenger set up the Aphra Behn Endowment Fund, named after the female poet. This fund was renamed the Ann Messenger Graduate Endowment Fund in 1996.
Despite Messenger's determination to fight her illness, the cancer continued to reoccur, and she passed away on February 1, 1996. Bill Messenger, who had taken early retirement in 1988 to care for Ann, passed away on June 15, 2003 due to complications from pneumonia and Alzheimer's Disease.
published
Full
Revised
Title of the fonds is based on the name of its creator.
Fonds consists of records relating to the personal and academic activites of Ann Messenger. Activities, events and topics documented include Messenger's social and academic activities while attending college and university; her marriage to Bill Messenger; her career as an academic, including her experiences as a young professor at Simon Fraser University; and her academic activities, including her research, writings, and publications. Fonds also includes correspondence of Bill Messenger and his father, Edmund Messenger.
Records include correspondence; publications, papers, articles, and reviews; notes, assignments, and examinations; course outlines, lesson plans, and lecture and tutorial notes; typescripts and proofs; journals; photographs and postcards; applications and appointment forms; and a text book.
Department of English; Photographic materials; Textual records; Women; Arts and culture; Community life
The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by Bill Messenger in one accession in 2003 and Betty Schellenberg in one accession in 2003.
No further accruals are expected.
For other material relating to Ann Messenger, see the William Messenger fonds at the University of British Columbia Archives.
One file (F-176-1-2-0-12) has been restricted in part because it includes a document containing 3rd party personal information; researchers can access the file minus the restricted document. All other files are open.
File and item lists are available.
- Personal correspondence, 1935, 1951-1974, 1987; F-176-1; 81 cm of textual records 17 photographs; General note: photographs are located in sub-series 1 and 2.
  published
  Series consists of correspondence between Ann Messenger and her parents, and incoming correspondence from friends.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files are generally arranged chronologically. Photographs have been left in folders with correspondence, so as not to lose their context.
  The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by William Messenger in one accession in 2003.
  A file list is available.
  - Correspondence with parents, 1951-1974, 1987; F-176-1-1; 47 cm of textual records 2 photographs; General note: photographs are located in files 26 and 27.
    Sub-series consists of Ann Messenger's correspondence with her parents, Raymond and Lillian Parshall. Correspondence includes letters written to her parents while she was studying at Oberlin College, Oxford University, and Cornell University. Correspondence also includes letters written while Messenger was working at Princeton University and after her marriage to Bill Messenger, while living in Philadelphia, California, and Vancouver, British Columbia. Includes details of Messenger's daily activities, including social and academic activities, her experiences as a young woman in the 1950s and 1960s, travels in Europe, and the general culture of the time. Vancouver correspondence refers to Ann and Bill's experiences as young professors at the University of British Columbia and Simon Fraser University. Sub-series also includes letters written to Ann, and Bill, by her parents between 1957 and 1974.
    The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files are generally arranged chronologically.
    Raymond Parshall; Lillian Parshall
    - Letters to her parents, 1951; F-176-1-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 176-1)
      Textual records
      Open
    - Letters to her parents, 1952; F-176-1-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 176-1)
    - Letters to her parents, 1953; F-176-1-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 176-1)
    - Letters to her parents, 1954; F-176-1-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 176-1)
    - Letters to her parents, 1955; F-176-1-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 176-1)
    - Letters to her parents, 1956; F-176-1-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 176-1)
    - Letters to her parents, 1957; F-176-1-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 176-1)
    - Letters to her parents, 1958; F-176-1-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 176-2)
    - Letters to her parents, 1959; F-176-1-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 176-2)
    - Letters to her parents, 1960; F-176-1-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 176-2)
    - Letters to her parents, 1961; F-176-1-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 176-2)
    - Letters to her parents, 1962; F-176-1-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 176-2)
    - Letters to her parents, 1963; F-176-1-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 176-2)
    - Letters to her parents, 1964; F-176-1-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 176-2)
    - Letters to her parents, 1965; F-176-1-1-0-15 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters to her parents, 1966; F-176-1-1-0-16 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters to her parents, 1967; F-176-1-1-0-17 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters to her parents, 1968; F-176-1-1-0-18 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters to her parents, 1969; F-176-1-1-0-19 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters to her parents, 1970; F-176-1-1-0-20 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters to her parents, 1971; F-176-1-1-0-21 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters to her parents, 1972; F-176-1-1-0-22 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters to her parents, 1973; F-176-1-1-0-23 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters to her mother, 1987; F-176-1-1-0-24 (Archival box - standard 176-3)
    - Letters from her parents, 1957 to 1974, vol. 1, 1957 - 1974; F-176-1-1-0-25 (Archival box - standard 176-4)
    - Letters from her parents, 1957 to 1974, vol. 2, 1966 - 1967; F-176-1-1-0-26 (Archival box - standard 176-4)
      Textual records; Photographic materials
    - Letters from her parents, 1957 to 1974, vol. 3, 1967 - 1970; F-176-1-1-0-27 (Archival box - standard 176-4)
    - Letters from her parents, 1957 to 1974, vol. 4, 1967 - 1969; F-176-1-1-0-28 (Archival box - standard 176-4)
  - Correspondence from friends, 1935, 1951-1976; F-176-1-2; 35 cm of textual records 15 photographs; General note: photographs are located in files 2 and 3.
    Sub-series consists of correspondence received by Messenger from friends, including friends that Messenger met while attending university and at work.
    One file (F-176-1-2-0-12) has been restricted in part because it includes a document containing 3rd party personal information; researchers can access the file minus the restricted document. All other files are open.
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 1, 1935 - 1957; F-176-1-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 176-4)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 2, 1952 - 1962; F-176-1-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 176-4)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976 [includes photographs], vol. 3, 1954 - 1958; F-176-1-2-0-3 (Archival box - standard 176-5)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 4, 1954 - 1964; F-176-1-2-0-4 (Archival box - standard 176-5)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 5, 1955 - 1968; F-176-1-2-0-5 (Archival box - standard 176-5)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 6, 1956 - 1960; F-176-1-2-0-6 (Archival box - standard 176-5)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 7, 1960 - 1966; F-176-1-2-0-7 (Archival box - standard 176-6)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 8, 1966 - 1967; F-176-1-2-0-8 (Archival box - standard 176-6)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 9, 1967 - 1969; F-176-1-2-0-9 (Archival box - standard 176-6)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 10, 1967 - 1972; F-176-1-2-0-10 (Archival box - standard 176-6)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 11, 1971 - 1973; F-176-1-2-0-11 (Archival box - standard 176-6)
    - Letters from friends, misc., 1935, 1951 to 1976, vol. 12, 1973 - 1976; F-176-1-2-0-12 (Archival box - standard 176-7)
      Restricted in part
    - Letters from friends (postcards), 1954 - 1972; F-176-1-2-0-13 (Archival box - standard 176-7)
    - Shakespeare's birthday party materials, 1964; F-176-1-2-0-14 (Archival box - standard 176-7)
      William Shakespeare; Textual records
    - Journal: books and comments, 1952 - 1995; F-176-1-2-0-15 (Archival box - standard 176-7)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-176-item1.
- Academic writings and correspondence, 1952 - 1999; F-176-2; 34 cm of textual records; Dates of creation: Material dating from after Ann Messenger's death on February 1, 1996 was created by William Messenger.
  Series consists of records relating to Messenger's academic career and activities, in particular, her writings and correspondence of an academic nature. Includes material relating to the research, writing, editing, publishing, and distribution of articles and books written or edited by Messenger. Series also includes correspondence with colleagues involving collaboration or Messenger's advising on and editing of papers, articles, or other publications. Some material relates to Messenger's acceptance into graduate school, teaching position appointments, and sick leave. Records include correspondence, reviews, papers, journal, notes, proofs and typescripts, and application and appointment forms.
  Files were generally arranged chronologically by the archivist.
  The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by William Messenger in one accession in 2003 and by Betty Schellenberg in one accession in 2003.
  - Academic writings and correspondence - general, 1956 - 1995; F-176-2-1; 15 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of records relating to Messenger's academic activities, such as article and book writing and editing; research; criticism, review, editorial and advisory work for various publications and papers; and correspondence and collaboration with colleagues. Sub-series also contains some material pertaining to Messenger's applications for graduate school and teaching positions, position appointments, and sick leave. Records include correspondence, reviews, papers, a journal, notes, and application and appointment forms.
    File F-176-2-1-0-12 [Sick leave correspondence], was added to the sub-series by the archivist on May 18, 2011. This file contains materials that appear to have been removed from the fonds during its initial processing--possibly due to the sensitive subject matter and/or personal information they contain--and placed in the fonds' collection file. The materials were not in any known original order, and were arranged chronologically by the archivist.
    - Teaching and grad school correspondence, 1956 - 1966; F-176-2-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 176-7)
    - Cary: article and notes for "Horse's Mouth" - similes and correspondence, 1968 - 1971; F-176-2-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 176-7)
      Joyce Cary; Textual records
    - Old reviews - odds and ends, 1974 - 1984; F-176-2-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 176-7)
    - Correspondence related to CEET edition of [Frances] Brooke's "Emily Montague", 1981 - 1984; F-176-2-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 176-7)
      Centre for Editing Early Canadian Texts; Frances Brookes; Textual records
    - Isobel Grundy (incomplete), 1985 - 1995; F-176-2-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 176-7)
      Isobel Grundy; Textual records
    - Correspondence: Rizzo [Betty], 1985 - 1995; F-176-2-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
      Rizzo, Betty; Textual records
    - Lambert, B. (encyclopedia entry - related correspondence and biographical dictionary entry), 1986 - 1987; F-176-2-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
      Lambert, Betty; Textual records
    - His and Hers: letters (misc.), reviews, sales, 1986 - 1992; F-176-2-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
    - Colleagues press business; UPHAUS et al., 1987 - 1991; F-176-2-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
    - Correspondence: Barbara McGovern, 1988 - 1995; F-176-2-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
      McGovern, Barbara; Textual records
    - Susan Goulding, 1994 - 1995; F-176-2-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
      Susan Goulding; Textual records
    - [Sick leave correspondence], 1989 - 1996; F-176-2-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
  - "Dinarbas" correspondence, 1984 - 1995; F-176-2-2; 2 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of correspondence relating to Messenger's efforts to have a new edition of Ellis Cornelia Knight's "Dinarbas" published. Includes correspondence relating to her role as editor, the book's publication, and sales of the book.
    Ellis Cornelia Knight
    The records were donated to the Simon Fraser University Archives by Betty Schellenberg in one accession in 2003.
    - "Dinarbas" - old correspondence, 1984 - 1988; F-176-2-2-0-1 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
    - Correspondence related to publication and sales of "Dinarbas", 1987 - 1995; F-176-2-2-0-2 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
  - "Pastoral Tradition and the Female Talent" correspondence and proof, 1988 - 1995; F-176-2-3; 6 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of correspondence and a proof relating to Messenger's research for, and the publication of, her book "Pastoral Tradition and the Female Talent: Studies in Augustan Poetry," which was published posthumously in 1999.
    - S.S. etc. (A.M.S.) books - correspondence and business, 1988 - 1995; F-176-2-3-0-1 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
    - Pastoral research correspondence, 1989 - 1992; F-176-2-3-0-2 (Archival box - standard 176-8)
    - Proof: "Pastoral Tradition and the Female Talent", vol. 1, [199-?]; F-176-2-3-0-3 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Proof: "Pastoral Tradition and the Female Talent", vol. 2, [199-?]; F-176-2-3-0-4 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Proof: "Pastoral Tradition and the Female Talent", vol. 3, [199-?]; F-176-2-3-0-5 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Proof: "Pastoral Tradition and the Female Talent", vol. 4, [199-?]; F-176-2-3-0-6 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
  - "Woman and Poet in the Eighteenth Century" correspondence and typescript, 1986 - 1999; F-176-2-4; 12 cm of textual records
    Sub-series consists of correspondence and a typescript relating to Messenger's book "Woman and Poet in the Eighteenth Century: The Life of Mary Whateley Darwall (1738-1825)," published posthumously in 1999. Correspondence relates to Messenger's research for the book, and its publication. Sub-series also includes correspondence of Bill Messenger pertaining to the publication and distribution of the book following Ann's death.
    Mary Whateley Darwall
    - Apprenticeships [Mary Whateley Darwell book], 1986 - 1987; F-176-2-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - M.W.D. [Mary Whateley Darwall]: new/unfinished/ongoing, 1989 - 1992; F-176-2-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence re: 18th C., 1992 - 1995; F-176-2-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Correspondence with "Woman and Poet in the Eighteenth Century..." publisher, July 1993 - August 1993; F-176-2-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Typescript: "Woman and Poet in the Eghteenth Century…", vol. 1, 1993; F-176-2-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Typescript: "Woman and Poet in the Eghteenth Century…", vol. 2, 1993; F-176-2-4-0-6 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Typescript: "Woman and Poet in the Eghteenth Century…", vol. 3, 1993; F-176-2-4-0-7 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Typescript: "Woman and Poet in the Eghteenth Century…", vol. 4, 1993; F-176-2-4-0-8 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Typescript: "Woman and Poet in the Eghteenth Century…", vol. 5, 1993; F-176-2-4-0-9 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - Typescript: "Woman and Poet in the Eghteenth Century…", vol. 6, 1993; F-176-2-4-0-10 (Archival box - standard 176-9)
    - MWD [Mary Whateley Darwall] - PUFF, 1994; F-176-2-4-0-11 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
    - Correspondence: regarding "Woman and Poet in the Eighteenth Century…" [Bill Messenger], 1997 - 1999; F-176-2-4-0-12 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
    - Correspondence: Beoley [Bill Messenger], 1999; F-176-2-4-0-13 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
- University papers, assignments and notes, 1951 - 1960; F-176-3; 18 cm of textual records
  Series consists of records relating to Messenger's studies in literature at Oberlin College, Oxford University, and Cornell University. Includes papers, notes and assignments, examinations, and a text book.
  The arrangement was provided by the archivist. Files were arranged first chronologically, then according to type of material, and then alphabetically within the same type of material.
  - Paper: English Literature: "Of This Time of This Place" analysis, 1951; F-176-3-0-0-1 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Text book: "Reading French poetry: A guide to the understanding of French poetry for English-speaking students" [with notations by Messenger], 1951; F-176-3-0-0-2 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Examination booklets - Oberlin College, 1952 - 1954; F-176-3-0-0-3 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Notes and assignments: Restoration and 18th Century, Oberlin, Mr. Shaver, 1952 - 1953; F-176-3-0-0-4 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Notes and assignments: Modern Poetry, Oberlin, Mr. Hoover, 1953 - 1954; F-176-3-0-0-5 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Notes and assignments: Principles of Literary Criticism, Oberlin, Mr. Bongiorno, 1953 - 1954; F-176-3-0-0-6 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Papers: The Art and Thought of John Donne: A Series of Seminar Papers, 1953 - 1954; F-176-3-0-0-7 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Paper: Romantic Poets, Mr. Shaver, 18 November 1953; F-176-3-0-0-8 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Notes: Drama: Greek and Roman - plots and criticism, 1954; F-176-3-0-0-9 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Notes and assignments: Milton, Mr. Bongiorno, Oberlin, 1954 - 1955; F-176-3-0-0-10 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Paper: "A Critical Analysis of T.S. Eliot's Play, "The Cocktail Party", 1954; F-176-3-0-0-11 (Archival box - standard 176-10)
  - Papers: Principles of Literary Criticism, 1954 - 1955; F-176-3-0-0-12 (Archival box - standard 176-11)
  - Reading lists: bibliographies, 1954; F-176-3-0-0-13 (Archival box - standard 176-11)
  - Notes and assignments: Classical Literature in Translation, Oberlin, 1955; F-176-3-0-0-14 (Archival box - standard 176-11)
  - Papers: The Art and Thought of John Donne, 1955; F-176-3-0-0-15 (Archival box - standard 176-11)
    John Donne; Textual records
  - Oxford essays I, vol. 1, 1955 - 1957; F-176-3-0-0-16 (Archival box - standard 176-11)
  - Oxford essays I, vol. 2, 1955 - 1957; F-176-3-0-0-17 (Archival box - standard 176-11)
  - Oxford essays II, 1956 - 1957; F-176-3-0-0-18 (Archival box - standard 176-11)
  - Oxford essays, 1957; F-176-3-0-0-19 (Archival box - standard 176-11)
  - 18th Century, Cornell, Mr. Abrams, 1960; F-176-3-0-0-20 (Archival box - standard 176-11)
- Teaching materials, 1960 - 1981; F-176-4; 12 cm of textual records
  Series consists of teaching materials used by Messenger at Bucknell University, the University of California, San Francisco State University, the University of British Columbia, and Simon Fraser University. Includes course outlines, lesson plans, lecture and tutorial notes, assignments, examinations, and readings.
  Files were arranged chronologically by the archivist.